اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
When Musa(موسى) passed away; the leadership was handed down to Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون);
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) who is mentioned in Qur'an as a servant;
اَفَتَاهُ’
وَإِذْ قَالَ مُوسَىٰ لِفَتَاهُ
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) was a servant with Musa(موسى).
Being a servant with Musa(موسى), he was close to the revelation; close to the teacher,
and he was a righteous student of this teacher.
So when Musaعليه السلام passed away; the leadership was handed down to, Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون),
and Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) is Nabi(نَبِي);
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) is a Nabi(نَبِي), but he is not mentioned in Qur'an;
he is mentioned in the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
The name of Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) is not in Qur'an, but it is from Hadith(حديث), and it is in the Sahih Hadith(صحيح حديث).
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون), in English; Joshua.
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) became the leader of the children of Israel(اسرائيل).
The children of Israel(اسرائيل) were delivered to the Holy Land, and they were victorious; under his leadership.
this did not happen with Musaعليه السلام and it did not happen with Haroon(هارون).
Rather, it happened in the time of Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون).
Musa(موسى) and Haroon(هارون); they passed away when Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) were in the wilderness.
Rasool Allah ﷺ tells us a clue of the reason, why this victory was delayed.
The children of Israel(اسرائيل) who came out from Egypt, were raised up in servitude and slavery.
So, they were weak, and they were not fit for victory.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made them stay in the wilderness for 40 years.
Until, all of that generation passed away,
and a new generation who was raised up in freedom under the leadership and the teaching of Musa(موسى) and Haroon(هارون);
These are the ones who were given the victory to enter Jerusalem.
The ones who were raised up by Musa(موسى) and Haroon(هارون) in a free environment.
Because, the environment in Egypt was not suitable to raise up a generation of victory.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
لم یبقی معه احد ممن عبدالعجل
Rasool Ullah says; None of the ones; who worship the calf, entered into Jerusalem.
All of that old generation who worshipped the calf; were dead,
a new generation was raised up in the desert; in that harsh environment; under the teachings of Torah(تورة); under the hands of Musa(موسى) and Haroon(هارون);
these are the ones who were qualified for leadership.
We learned something interesting for them.
There's no doubt; that Musa(موسى) is the greatest Nabi(نَبِي) of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
How come did the victory happened in the time of Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون)?
And it tells us, there is not enough to have a leader.
Musa(موسى); is the best that Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) have seen, and he is the founder of this nation.
Nevertheless, victory did not happen on his hands even though he desired it so greatly.
He wanted to enter into the Holy Land.
And we know how much he desired that, that when the angel of death came to take his soul, he hit him,
and then; when he knew that this is his appointed time, he said, I will die now
but, oh Allah! Make me die as close to Jerusalem as possible.
رمي حجر
Throw of a stone.
He said; If I cannot enter into Jerusalem alive, at least bury me as close as possible to Jerusalem.
But that did not happen in the time of Musa(موسى), because the generation which were with Musa(موسى) did not deserve it.
So now when we keep on thinking that, I mean; we're waiting for Al-Mahdi(ال مهدى);
everyone is waiting for Al-Mahdi(المهدى).
It's not an issue of a Al-Mahdi(المهدى); If you're not ready; Al-Mahdi(المهدى) cannot do you anything.
The generation has to be ready and prepared for victory.
It's not an issue of a leader; the generation have to be ready and prepared.
And that's why, Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) were not able to enter into Jerusalem until, there was a suitable generation for victory.
And these are the ones who entered with Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون),
and we will see the miracle which Allahسُبحانه وتعالى performed for them.
When you have Allah on your side; don't worry! Allah will do everything for you.
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) was fighting with Al-Jababirah(الجبابره).
Al-Jababirah(الجبابره) were the people who were living in Jerusalem.
They were giants, powerful, tyrants.
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) led the children of Israel(اسرائيل) in that battle.
The fighting was furious.
The sun was about to set.
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) knew, that he would need more time; it's not enough for him.
He cannot win, except if the day is longer.
If they wait for the next day, the army will regroup and attack again.
So he needs the more time.
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) pointed to the sun and said;
أنت مأمورةٌ وأنا مأمورٌ
You are receiving orders, and I'm receiving orders.
Both of us are receiving orders from Allah; so stop!
He told the sun stop.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made the sun stop for Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون).
Until he finished, and destroyed the enemy, then the sun started moving again.
If you have Allahسُبحانه وتعالى on your side; don't worry! Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will take care of you.
It's not a matter of numbers, or weapons, or air force, or artillery, or battalions.
If you have Allah with you; Allah will help you.
He pointed to the sun; to stop! It stopped.
And this Hadith(حديث) is narrated by Al-Imam Ahmad(الاِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
غزا نبيٌّ من الأنبياءِ ،
فقال لقومِه : لا يتبعُني رجلٌ قد ملك بُضعَ امرأةٍ ،
وهو يُريدُ أن يبنيَ بها ولم يبْنِ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; One of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) went into war, and he told his army;
if any one of you just got married, you did not sleep with your wife yet, and you want to; then don't come with me.
And then he said;
ولا آخرُ قد بنَى بنيانًا ولمَّا يرفَعْ سقفَها
And if anybody is building a house, and he did not build the roof yet, then don't come with me.
What is the Nabi(نَبِي) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) telling his people;
If you got married to a woman, and you did not sleep with her yet, don't come with me.
If you are building a house, and you did not build the roof yet, don't come with me.
If you have bought some pregnant goats or pregnant camels, and you're waiting for them to deliver, don't come with me.
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) does not want anybody to come with him; if their hearts are attached to something else.
If your heart is with your wife, don't come with me.
If your heart is with your house, don't come with me.
If your heart is with the camels and goats, don't come with me.
He's not looking for numbers; he could gather a crowd and take them to war.
He said; No! I don't want you.
This battle needs people who have, Ikhlas(اِخْلَاص); who have sincerity.
If you're coming, and doing this half-heartedly; stay home.
And then, Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
فغزا ، فأدنَى من لقريةِ حين صلاةِ العصرِ ، أو قريبًا من ذلك ،
فقال للشَّمسِ : أنت مأمورةٌ وأنا مأمورٌ ،
اللَّهمَّ احبِسْها عليَّ شيئًا ، فحُبِست عليه ، حتَّى فتح اللهُ عليه ،
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; He fought; until it was time of Asr(عصر),
and then he told the sun; you are receiving orders, and I'm receiving orders, oh Allah! Stop the sun.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى stop the sun, until he achieved victory, and he won.
This is the story of Sayidina Yusha Bin Noon(سيدنا يوشع بن نون).
They won, and they entered into Jerusalem, and they started expanding their nation; under the banner of;
لا إلهَ إلاَّ اللَّه
Time past; few generations, maybe a few centuries, and then the enemies were regrouping and attacking again.
And there was a continuous Jihad(جهاد) with Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Under the leadership of one of their Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء);
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) came to their Nabi(نَبِي), and they told him;
Send us a king; so that we can fight under his leadership.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
أَلَمْ تَرَ إِلَى الْمَلَإِ مِن بَنِي إِسْرَائِيلَ مِن بَعْدِ مُوسَىٰ إِذْ قَالُوا لِنَبِيٍّ لَّهُمُ ابْعَثْ لَنَا مَلِكًا
Have you not thought about the group of the children of Israel(اسرائيل) after the time of Musa(موسى),
when they said to a prophet of theirs; appoint for us a king and we will fight in Allah's way?
They came to their Nabi(نَبِي), and they told them; We want to fight in the sake of Allah.
Their Nabi(نَبِي) was very wise.
قَالَ هَلْ عَسَيْتُمْ إِن كُتِبَ عَلَيْكُمُ الْقِتَالُ أَلَّا تُقَاتِلُوا ۖ
He said; Would you then refrain from fighting, when fighting was prescribed for you?
He said; You're asking for fighting; but when fighting is prescribed on you, will you fight?
Because it's easy to claim, that you're willing to fight.
And people talk, but rarely do we find anybody walking the talk?
People say that; We're willing to fight in the sake of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, and they're giving out these sermons, and everybody is motivated and encouraged.
But then, when it comes to the real situation; people back out.
And the Nabi(نَبِي) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told them, he said; Now you're asking for fighting; what if it is prescribed on you, Will you then fight?
They said; Definitely!
وَمَا لَنَا أَلَّا نُقَاتِلَ فِي سَبِيلِ اللَّهِ وَقَدْ أُخْرِجْنَا مِن دِيَارِنَا وَأَبْنَائِنَا ۖ
Why shouldn't we fight in the sake of Allah, when we have been driven out of our homes and our children.
They have kicked us out of our land; how come we will not fight?
And we will fight in the sake of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And they gave their promises, and they said; We will fight in the sake of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; Don't worry! We will fight.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَلَمَّا كُتِبَ عَلَيْهِمُ الْقِتَالُ تَوَلَّوْا إِلَّا قَلِيلًا مِّنْهُمْ ۗ
But when fighting was ordered for them, they turned away; all except a few of them.
We should never be fooled by the claims that we hear, and the talk.
Because talk is free, It doesn't cost you anything to talk; but fighting in the sake of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى cost you a lot.
You can make a claim that you will open Jerusalem if you want.
Talking big is easy, but the sacrifice and especially long term sacrifice which he had needs, that is difficult.
Jihad(جهاد) is not only sacrifice, but it's a long term sacrifice and that is, where people fail.
If you are asked to sacrifice in one time; you could be fired up with a speech
and then you would give out your money for example; and you would sacrifice, that could happen.
But when you're asked to sacrifice for a long period; and you're suffering hardship for a long time; that is what causes people to fail.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); they said;
We're gonna fight; why shouldn't we fight, and we were driven out of our homes and driven out of our children?
When Allahسُبحانه وتعالى prescribed fighting on them, they didn't.
But now, it's too late to back out, because the orders are the revealed.
They asked for a king, they asked for a leader; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى provided them with one.
Their Nabi(نَبِي) said;
وَقَالَ لَهُمْ نَبِيُّهُمْ إِنَّ اللَّهَ قَدْ بَعَثَ لَكُمْ طَالُوتَ مَلِكًا ۚ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has sent to you Talut(طالوت) as a king.
Allah has appointed for you a king, and he is Talut(طالوت).
Now, these people who asked to fight in the sake of Allah; they were the first one to argue with the commandment of their Nabi(نَبِي).
They came to the Nabi(نَبِي), and they said; We want a leader,
when they were provided with a leader; they started arguing and they said; We don't want it.
They are asking for a king, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى provided them with the leader, and then they said; We don't want him.
Why?
They gave two reasons.
They gave two reasons; why they disagree with the appointment of Talut(طالوت) as a king.
قَالُوا أَنَّىٰ يَكُونُ لَهُ الْمُلْكُ عَلَيْنَا وَنَحْنُ أَحَقُّ بِالْمُلْكِ مِنْهُ وَلَمْ يُؤْتَ سَعَةً مِّنَ الْمَالِ ۚ
Two reasons:
Number one; He's not from the nobility;
he's not from the noble families.
Number two; He's not wealthy.
These are the two reasons.
How can he be a king, when he does not belong to the high class?
And how can he be a king when he is not wealthy?
And this is the nature of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); what they consider to be success in life; is the status of which class you come from,
because they always use race as an issue.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); the Jews, it's an issue to them; We are the chosen people, we are the special people,
you are the Gentiles, you are lower class.
So race is important to them.
And then the second issue of money.
These are the criteria that they use; race and money.
And this is a disease that is in the hearts of the children of Israel(اسرائيل); Al-Yahood(ال يهود),
and it's also a disease that exists somewhat among us.
We consider people to be successful, according to how much money they have.
What did they say?
How much is he, what?
Worth.
How much is he worth?
So we qualify the person according to how much Money he has.
When you say, how much the person is worth?
What you're talking about?
His money;
he is worth a billion, he is worth a million.
If he doesn't have any money; he's worth nothing.
His Eeman(ايمان) doesn't matter?
His Salah(صلوة) doesn't matter?
His Deen(دِيْن) doesn't matter?
If he doesn't have any money; he is worth nothing.
Their Nabi(نَبِي) is teaching them that, this is wrong; he told them;
إِنَّ اللَّهَ اصْطَفَاهُ عَلَيْكُمْ
Allah has chosen him among you; That's it.
This is enough to settle the argument; Allah is the one who chose him.
Don't argue! His ancestry, his ethnicity, his race, doesn't matter, his wealth doesn't matter.
Why?
Allah has chosen him.
So that could have been the end of the conversation.
Allah has chosen him, peri.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wants to teach us; how to choose leaders?
Therefore, the Nabi(نَبِي) has told them two qualifications you should be looking for; when you're looking for a leader.
They gave two reasons why he shouldn't be a leader;
their Nabi(نَبِي) gave them two reasons why he should be the leader.
He said;
إِنَّ اللَّهَ اصْطَفَاهُ عَلَيْكُمْ وَزَادَهُ بَسْطَةً فِي الْعِلْمِ وَالْجِسْمِ ۖ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has increased him amply in two things; knowledge and strength.
Allah has given him two things; knowledge and strength.
The word knowledge is defined according to the job, which you are appointing the leader to.
Why am I saying this?
Because many times whenever we say knowledge; our minds would immediately take us to Fiqh(فقه)
and that's not necessarily in the case.
If a person is going to be appointed as a military leader, then he should have a lot of knowledge in fighting; in war.
And that's why, Rasool Allah ﷺ appointed Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) to be the general; the Ameer(أمير) of the army,
but it wasn't Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was appointed to be the Khalifah(خليفه).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was appointed to be the Khalifah(خليفه).
Every position has its knowledge that is required.
Talut(طالوت) had the knowledge, he needed for the job of leading Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) in Jihad(جهاد), and he had strength.
And again, strength is defined according to the job.
It's not a matter of physical strength.
You don't need to have a body builder for every job.
In this job, you need to be physically strong.
But in other types of jobs that needs to have mental strength, or strength of wealth, or strength of heart, it depends on the type of job.
But these are the two things; you should look for in the leader; knowledge and strength.
وَزَادَهُ بَسْطَةً فِي الْعِلْمِ وَالْجسْد
Then he said;
وَاللَّهُ يُؤْتِي مُلْكَهُ مَن يَشَاءُ ۚ
Allah gives the kingdom to whomever He wills.
It's not up to you; it's up to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
وَقَالَ لَهُمْ نَبِيُّهُمْ إِنَّ ءَايَةَ مُلْكِهِۦٓ أَن يَأْتِيَكُمُ ٱلتَّابُوتُ فِيهِ سَكِينَةٌ مِّن رَّبِّكُمْ وَبَقِيَّةٌ
وَبَقِيَّةٌ مِّمَّا تَرَكَ ءَالُ مُوسَىٰ وَءَالُ هَٰرُونَ تَحْمِلُهُ ٱلْمَلَٰٓئِكَةُ ۚ
إِنَّ فِى ذَٰلِكَ لَءَايَةً لَّكُمْ إِن كُنتُم مُّؤْمِنِينَ۝
Allah to strengthen their hearts is going to appoint; Talut(طالوت) as a king through a ceremony,
and this ceremony would be a miracle from Allah; to strengthen their hearts so that they would accept him as a leader.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is gonna provide a miracle; Ayah(آية).
That Ayah(آية) was At-Taboot(التَّابُوت).
At-Taboot(التَّابُوت) is a casket.
In that casket, were some of the belongings of Musa(موسى) and Haroon(هارون).
And Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) used to consider that to be Barakah(بركة), because it is left behind from the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء).
And between them and Musa(موسى) are centuries; few hundreds of years.
So they have been separated from Musa(موسى) through a long history.
They had some of the belongings of Musa(موسى) and Haroon(هارون) in a casket, and they used to consider that to be Barakah(بركة) for them,
because it's left behind from the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
What happened is; the enemy was able to take hold of this.
And the enemy took it away from them.
This Ayah(آية); Miracle that Allah has gonna give them is that;
this Tabut(تابوت); casket will be delivered by the angels to Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
So the angels carried this casket, and brought it back to Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
And in it; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى also says is; Sakinah(سكينة); Tranquility; peace for you.
This belongs to the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء); Allah will bring it back to you. So it's gonna be Sakinah(سكينة) for you.
Talut(طالوت) was appointed as a king.
فَلَمَّا فَصَلَ طَالُوتُ بِالْجُنُودِ
When Talut(طالوت) set out with the army.
Talut(طالوت) now, recruited all of the men, and he set out with them; Fasala(فَصَلَ)
فَلَمَّا فَصَلَ طَالُوتُ بِالْجُنُودِ
Meaning; that he separated himself from the rest of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
All of the children, and the women, and the elderly are left behind and now, Talut(طالوت) is with the; fighters.
He has the soldiers with him.
As-Suddi(السدى); one of the Mufassireen(مفسرين) says; they numbered 80,000.
His army was 80,000 soldiers; men.
Talut(طالوت) is not looking for numbers.
Talut(طالوت) knows that what he is facing ahead; needs an iron will.
It needs patience, it needs strength.
Therefore, he's gonna take his ummah(امة); he is gonna take this army, through a series of tests.
He's not gonna take them and fight.
He's not looking for a crowd.
He's looking for strong soldiers who can fight with him.
Because Talut(طالوت); out of his wisdom knew; that if there are any weak soldiers with us, they're gonna cause us more harm than benefit.
And we know that from the Seerah(سيرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
In the Battle of the Tabook(تبوك); the Munafiqeen(مُنافقين) were coming Rasool Allah ﷺ, and everyone was giving an excuse to stay behind.
I mean, they were inventing excuses.
One of them even came and said; Oh Rasool Allah ﷺ! I fear the Fitnah(فِتْنَه) of woman.
I don't wanna go with you and fight because, if I see women then, I would lose my mind.
That is the excuse that he gave.
He said; Please let me stay here!
Munafiqeen(مُنافقين); they were coming to Rasool Allah ﷺ and everyone was giving an excuse.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ knows that they are Munafiqeen(مُنافقين), and he is telling them; stay behind.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَلَوْ أَرَادُوا الْخُرُوجَ لَأَعَدُّوا لَهُ عُدَّةً
If they were serious that they wanted to fight, they would have found ways to prepare for it.
But they're not serious, they don't want to fight, these excuses are fake.
If they were serious; if they were true in their intentions to fight;
لَأَعَدُّوا لَهُ عُدَّةً
They would have prepared for it.
Now, they're waiting till the last moment and then, they're coming and saying;
I have business that is not done yet.
Allah is saying;
وَلَوْ أَرَادُوا الْخُرُوجَ لَأَعَدُّوا لَهُ عُدَّةً
If they were serious, they would have prepared for it early.
And they would have been able to go.
وَلَٰكِن كَرِهَ اللَّهُ انبِعَاثَهُمْ فَثَبَّطَهُمْ وَقِيلَ اقْعُدُوا مَعَ الْقَاعِدِينَ۝
Allah did not want them to go out.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made them stay behind.
Allah does not want them to go out with his Nabi(نَبِي);
why?
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
لَوْ خَرَجُواْ فِيكُم مَّا زَادُوكُمْ إِلَّا خَبَالًا
If they went out with you, they would have cost you nothing but weakness.
These soldiers; if they come out with you, oh Muhammadﷺ! They gonna cause you weakness.
Because when the battle starts, and the screws are tightened, then they gonna fail.
So instead of having a brother next to your side helping you in the battlefield; you're gonna have somebody who is putting fear in your heart,
telling you; Let's run away!
Therefore, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said;
فَثَبَّطَهُمْ
Allah did not want them to go out, and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made them stay behind.
Because if they went with you, they would cause you nothing but weakness;
خَبَالًا
Talut(طالوت) did not want this quality of people to come with him.
He did not want them in his army.
And we know in the Battle of Hunayn(حنين); because there were many new Muslims in the army,
after Fath Makkah(فتح مكه), there were many who just became Muslim.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ opened Makkah(مكه), that was the hugest army ever that's Rasool Allah ﷺ had.
And one of the Sahabah(صحابه) looked at this army and said;
لن نغلب الیوم القلۃ
We're not going to lose because of numbers.
Numbers is not going to be factored in this war.
Look at this huge number we have.
What happened in the Battle of Hunayn(حنين)?
As soon as they received the first blow from the enemy; they were running in every direction.
They were running in every direction.
Talut(طالوت) didn't want these with him.
So he's going to take them through a test.
This test is;
إِنَّ اللَّهَ مُبْتَلِيكُم بِنَهَرٍ
Allah is going to test you with a river.
Talut(طالوت) made them march; in the desert.
And he made them thirsty, exhausted and tired.
And then when they saw water in front of their eyes;
Talut(طالوت) said; Don't drink!
Thirsty, exhausted, tired.
Some of them are maybe wondering that we might face death, if we don't drink.
Talut(طالوت) said; Don't drink!
مَن شَرِبَ مِنْهُ فَلَيْسَ مِنِّي
Whoever drinks, does not belong to me, you cannot come with me anymore.
وَمَن لَّمْ يَطْعَمْهُ فَإِنَّهُ مِنِّي
And if you do not drink, then you can come with me.
إِلَّا مَنِ اغْتَرَفَ غُرْفَةً بِيَدِهِ ۚ
Or if you drink one handful, then you can still come with me.
So you either don't drink;
or if you drink you only drink one handful; just one hand, and one hand cannot take much; not two hands, one hand.
I assume that; it is easier not to drink, rather than take one drink.
Because when you take that first drink; Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) is going to make it taste, the best sip of water that you ever had in your life.
And in the end, the result was 80,000 went through this admission test.
And only 4000 graduated, out of 80,000 76,000 of them drank from the river.
Only 4000 crossed it to the other side.
The rest failed from the first test.
76,000 were left Behind.
Talut(طالوت) is not looking for numbers.
These are men who are willing to go and fight with him.
He said; Don't come with me! You're not allowed.
It's a test of will.
Because he wants to have men with him, who are willing to stand up; against temptations,
and who are going to be patient against hardship.
They're willing to stand up against the strong temptations.
And in the same time, they are very patient and enduring hardship.
In the end, 4000 remained with him.
When they cross to the other side of the river; and the ones who are left behind with Talut(طالوت) were only 4000.
Then that was another test for them.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَلَمَّا جَاوَزَهُ هُوَ وَالَّذِينَ آمَنُوا مَعَهُ قَالُوا لَا طَاقَةَ لَنَا الْيَوْمَ بِجَالُوتَ وَجُنُودِهِ ۚ
They said; We have no way of fighting Jalut(جالوت).
4000; do you want us to fight Jalut(جالوت), look at his army?
There's no way!
The believers;
قَالَ الَّذِينَ يَظُنُّونَ أَنَّهُم مُّلَاقُو اللَّهِ
The ones; who are sure, that they are going to meet Allah, they said;
كَم مِّن فِئَةٍ قَلِيلَةٍ غَلَبَتْ فِئَةً كَثِيرَةً بِإِذْنِ اللَّهِ ۗ
How many times; has a small group defeated a larger group; with the will of Allah?
It's not a matter of numbers, who are these we're speaking?
The ones who are sure that, they will meet Allah.
So, they're not thinking in terms of this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا); but they're thinking in terms of meeting Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
The others are telling them;
No, let's be real! Let's be real! 4000 against this huge army; there is no way we can win.
They're thinking in terms of the logic of this world.
What they can see with their eyes?
I can see with my eyes; the larger army, they can defeat us.
They're not believing in the unseen.
So now, another group failed.
In the end, Talut(طالوت) was left with the pure; the best of the children of Israel(اسرائيل);
314; Out of 80,000; 314 remained with Talut(طالوت).
The Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, it is narrated that, they said;
We were told that, the number of Mujahideen(مجاهدين) or fighters, which were with Talut(طالوت); was the same number as the ones who fought in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
ثلاثمائة وعشرة
More than, 310.
These are the ones, who remained with Talut(طالوت); out of 80,000.
Talut(طالوت) took them through test; that would separate between the men and the boys; set them aside.
He take the strong in one side, and the weak and the unfit on the other side.
In the end he was left with 310 or 314.
These 314 Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says about them;
وَلَمَّا بَرَزُوا لِجَالُوتَ وَجُنُودِهِ
And when they faced
جَالُوتَ وَجُنُودِهِ
Before that, Talut(طالوت) was taking them through tests, to see; how patient they are, how strong they are, how determined are they?
But now, when they are facing the enemy; he is putting all of that aside.
It's not your strength, it is not your patience, it is not your will.
All of these are means; now it is pending on Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So we use the means before.
These means; you prepare for them before the battle.
But then when you are in the battlefield; you do not depend on the means anymore.
You depend on Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Rasool Allah ﷺ lined up the army; gave them instructions and orders in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
But then when it was time to fighting; what did Rasool Allah ﷺ do?
He went on a hilltop and started making Dua(دُعَا).
Now, you put your whole dependency on Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
At that moment, when they were facing Jalut(جالوت); what did they say?
قَالُوا رَبَّنَا أَفْرِغْ عَلَيْنَا صَبْرًا
Now they are directing their call to Allah; Oh Allah! Shower us or cover us with patience,
Allahu Akbar(الله اكبر)!
They're not asking for patience; they're saying;
أَفْرِغْ عَلَيْنَا صَبْرًا
Oh Allah! Cover us with patience.
Because, you don't need a little bit of patience.
You do not need a small amount; you need a lot.
So they said;
أَفْرِغْ عَلَيْنَا
Afrigh(أَفْرِغْ) is like; you have big bucket, and you're pouring it over someone.
That is; Ifraagh(اِفرَاغ).
أَفْرِغْ عَلَيْنَا صَبْرًا
Pour on us patience.
وَثَبِّتْ أَقْدَامَنَا
And make our feet firm.
وَٱنصُرْنَا عَلَى ٱلْقَوْمِ ٱلْكَٰفِرِينَ۝
And give us victory over the nonbelievers.
The battle started.
A huge army was fighting the small army.
فِئَةٍ قَلِيلَةٍ وَالطَّالُوت
Jalut(جالوت) was the king of the enemy;
powerful, huge, strong man with arrogance and pride; fighting in the battlefield; asking for anyone to challenge him.
Who dares to fight me?
Talut(طالوت) said; Who will go out and get rid of him; who will eliminate Jalut(جالوت)?
He didn't get any response.
A young man; short.
He was described by; Wahb Ibn Munabieh(وھب ابن منبہ) As a short man came up to Talut(طالوت) and said; I will!
Talut(طالوت) saw that this is a child; so he made the announcement again; Who will go and face Jalut(جالوت)?
Nobody responded except this young man.
And for the third time; nobody came except him.
Talut(طالوت) said; Then go!
This young man was armed with a slingshot; with a slingshot.
But he was armed with Eeman(ايمان) and trust in Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in the heart.
He went up to Jalut(جالوت) and challenged him.
Jalut(جالوت) said; I don't want to fight you; you are a kid; send somebody stronger; I don't want to kill you.
This young man said; But I want to kill you.
And he put a small pebble in his slingshot, and he shot Jalut(جالوت), and Jalut(جالوت) was dead.
He eliminated the king of the enemy.
And the battle was over.
And this young man was Dawoodعليه السلام.
At that time, he was not a Nabi(نَبِي) yet.
He was a young fighter in the army.
After that, he was the one who inherited the kingdom from Talut(طالوت).
And now, the children of Israel(اسرائيل) are going to enter into their golden age under the leadership of Dawoodعليه السلام and Sulaimanعليه السلام.
But this was built on the shoulders of these 314 men who fought in that battle.
Just like the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) was established on the shoulders of the 300 and so who fought in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
That is how you establish Khilafah(خِلَافَه).
It's not by talking.
He establish it by the sacrifice.
And it's not an issue of numbers, but it's an issue of  men and strength in the hearts.
That is the best era; that Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) ever had.
After that it was their downfall.
After that it was the curse of their Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) on them.
It was their downfall; and it was the end until, they eventually were the nation whom Allahسُبحانه وتعالى was angry with.
Even though; we are done with the story of Musa(موسى), but we're not done with the story of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل)
and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) are going to continue with us until, we end the series of the lives of the prophets.
Until the end of the series; we're still going to be talking about this ummah(امة)
because every other Nabi(نَبِي) that we're going to talk about from now on, is from this nation; Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has made in the nation of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) and the nations of Al-Ulama(اَلعُلَمَا).
Out of them were the best scholars of their age, and the best people of their time.
It wasn't until, they neglected the book of Allah and throw it, behind their backs.
That is when Allahسُبحانه وتعالى put his wrath and anger on them.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَهَزَمُوهُم بِإِذْنِ اللَّهِ وَقَتَلَ دَاوُودُ جَالُوتَ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; So they routed them by Allah's leave and David killed Goliath.
وَآتَاهُ اللَّهُ الْمُلْكَ وَالْحِكْمَةَ وَعَلَّمَهُ مِمَّا يَشَاءُ ۗ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; And Allah gave him(David) the kingdom, after the death of Jalut(جالوت).
وَعَلَّمَهُ مِمَّا يَشَاءُ ۗ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى also taught him wisdom, and
عَلَّمَهُ مِمَّا يَشَاءُ ۗ
And He taught him other things, that He will.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given Sayidina Dawood(سيدناداؤد), kingdom, and He has given him; Al-Hikmah(الحكمة); wisdom,
and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has taught him knowledge.
Hikmah(حكمة) was interpreted as, good judgment, and the ability to run the affairs of the people.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given Sayidina Dawood(سيدناداؤد) some miracles and unique qualities.
Dawoodعليه السلام; first of all, had a beautiful voice.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was hearing; Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari(ابو موسى الاشعرى) who had the most beautiful voice among the Sahabah(صحابه) in recitation of Qur'an.
Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari(ابو موسى الاشعرى) had the most beautiful voice in reading Qur'an.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, when he heard him, read Qur'an, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
لقد أوتيت مزمارا من مزامير آل داود
You have been given a flute of the flutes of the family of Dawood(داؤد).
This does not mean a flute, literally, it means the beauty of the sound.
The sound was so beautiful, and Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari(ابو موسى الاشعرى);
You have part of that beautiful sound.
Dawood(داؤد)'s voice was so beautiful; in his Tasbeeh(تسبيح) and reading of their Qur'an, which was their book; the book of Dawood(داؤد).
Because, Dawoodعليه السلام; he received the book from Allah.
We know five books.
There are many other messengers, who received books from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, but we know the names of five.
Al-Qur'an(القرآن); which was revealed on Muhammadﷺ.
Al-Injeel(الانجيل); The Gospel; which was revealed on?
Eesa(عيسى); Jesus.
At-Torah(التورة)?
The Torah(تورة); which was revealed on Musa(موسى).
And then, Az-Zaboor(الزبور); which was revealed on?
Dawood(داؤد).
And then the final one was;
Suhuf Ibrahim(صُحُف اِبْراهِيْم);
The Scrolls; which were revealed to Ibrahim عليه السّلام.
Dawood(داؤد) would recite; Az-Zaboor(الزبور).
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made it so easy on him.
When Sayidina Dawood(سيدناداؤد) would read Qur'an and make Dhikr(ذكر); the mountains and the birds would join with him, and they would repeat after him.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَلَقَدْ آتَيْنَا دَاوُودَ مِنَّا فَضْلًا ۖ
يَا جِبَالُ أَوِّبِي مَعَهُ وَالطَّيْرَ ۖ
Awwibi(أَوِّبِي) means; Tarji'ah(ترجيه); repeat after him.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is commanding the mountains and the birds to repeat after Dawood(داؤد).
Imagine! Dawoodعليه السلام is reciting Qur'an, and the mountains and the birds are repeating after him.
Because, everything around us is making Tasbeeh(تسبيح) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; Everything is making Tasbeeh(تسبيح); everything is glorifying Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; but you do not know, their glorifying.
And what is the sound of lightning?
Thunder?
What is Thunder?
Thunder is a Tasbeeh(تسبيح) of Allah.
وَيُسَبِّحُ الرَّعْدُ بِحَمْدِهِ وَالْمَلَائِكَةُ مِنْ خِيفَتِهِ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says that; The thunder is making Tasbeeh(تسبيح).
That sound of the thunder, is Tasbeeh(تسبيح) of Allah; is glorifying of Allah.
Now tell this to a scientist; he's going to say,
What is this nonsense that you're talking about?
You don't know! Let me explain to you; what Thunder is?
He will tell you that, Thunder is the sound waves that come from the lightning.
When the lightning strikes, it causes a vacuum in the air, and that shock wave travels through the air,
and that is; what you hear in the form of thunder.
Well tell them; that is right!
And then give him an example.
Tell him; imagine! that there is an ant or a kingdom of ants.
These ants are scientists like you, and they want to do a research on human beings.
They heard that, there's a creation out there called human beings.
So this advanced Kingdom of ants, they want to study about this creature called Human Being.
So they send an ant a reporter; they send an ant to report about this human being.
This ant goes up to this human being, and is studying this human being and writing all of the observations.
The human being that was sitting, turns out to be a Muslim; he says; Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله)!
That Muslim; he say; Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله)!
So the ant is writing its observations;
the mouth opened, and the tongue moved, and air came out, and that is the voice that we heard.
It was due to the movement of the tongue, and the lips and, and the air coming out from the mouth, in a form of sound waves, that travel through the air.
And it will go down to the ant kingdom and report these findings.
The ant will say; I heard the voice coming out from that human being;
the mouth was moving, and the tongue was moving, and the sound wave came out and it travelled in the air.
That's the extent of the knowledge of the ant; because it doesn't understand the language of the human being.
But the human being; what was he saying?
He was saying; Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله)!
But the ant is not able to understand it.
So, it describes it as the physical motions that it can see.
The same thing with us; human beings.
We are describing the physical phenomena of thunder or any other voices that we hear in nature,
because we are uncapable of understanding the language of the thunder.
We're uncapable of understanding the language of the birds, or the language of the bees, or the language of any other beasts that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى created.
So we describe it in a scientific fashion and way.
And in reality; it is Tasbeeh(تسبيح).
يُسَبِّحُ الرَّعْدُ بِحَمْدِهِ
The Ra'ad(رَعَد) is making Tasbeeh(تسبيح).
The unique thing with Sayidina Dawoodعليه السلام and his son, Sulayman(سليمان), is that
they understood the language of the animals and the birds.
And Dawood(داؤد) had another quality that his son Sulayman(سليمان) did not have.
That, when Dawood(داؤد) make Tasbeeh(تسبيح); the creation around him would join him and Tasbeeh(تسبيح).
It is a miracle; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى gives the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء); miracles.
Sayidina Dawood(سيدناداؤد) would make Tasbeeh(تسبيح); the mountains are making Tasbeeh(تسبيح) with him, and the birds are making Tasbeeh(تسبيح) with him.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى also gave him another miracle.
And that is; Iron; steel would become soft in his hands, he could move it however he wishes.
وَأَلَنَّا لَهُ الْحَدِيدَ۝
We made iron soft in his hands.
Humans in that time, they had iron.
But the process of making tools out of it was very difficult and time consuming.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made iron soft in the hands of the Dawood(داؤد).
He would mold it however he wants.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى then taught him; how to make shields; armoury out of steel, in a new way.
So, it was a new invention.
Before that, they would make armory in the form of iron plates, which were solid.
So the soldier would have to wear that heavy iron plate, which has two downsides to it.
First of all, it's heavy.
The second downside is that; it prevents flexibility and movement.
Because, it's a solid plate of iron; steel.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى taught Dawood(داؤد); how to make armoury out of rings of iron?
So, he would make the iron into rings, and attach the rings together,
and attach rings to those rings until, he would make an armory that would cover the body.
And this prevents, and this eliminates the two downsides of the other armoury.
Because, it's very light in weight; rings are very light, and it's very flexible.
Because, it's rings you could move freely.
But it offers the same protection; because it is from iron.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَعَلَّمْنَٰهُ صَنْعَةَ لَبُوسٍۢ لَّكُمْ
We taught him; the making of metal coats.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى taught him; how to make these metal coats?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
لِتُحْصِنَكُم مِّنۢ بَأْسِكُمْ
So that, it will protect you in your fighting.
Allah is the one who taught him, how to do this.
In the other Ayah(آية) Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
أَنِ اعْمَلْ سَابِغَاتٍ وَقَدِّرْ فِي السَّرْدِ ۖ
Saying; Make you perfect coats of male; balancing well the rings of chain armour,
and work human righteously, truly I am also aware of what you do.
وَقَدِّرْ فِي السَّرْدِ ۖ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling Dawoodعليه السلام; Make the rings proportionate! Don't make them too large.
Because if they're too large; they could be penetrated.
And if they are too small; there could be some other negative aspects to it.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling Dawoodعليه السلام;
وَقَدِّرْ فِي السَّرْدِ ۖ
Make them the right size!
In modern terms; we would call this a new technological invention.
Even though, it will happen through a miracle with Dawoodعليه السلام.
But I'm getting to another point.
In modern terms; we call this a modern invention, just like a car, or a computer, or an airplane, or whatever.
Even though, we all believe that; everything is created by Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Somehow subconsciously, we attribute these things to the human beings who made them.
So we're always impressed with the manufacturer,
whether it be IBM, or Intel, or Toyota, or Sony, whatever manufacturer is making for us these new inventions.
And we always hold the scientists in high esteem, whether it is Isaac Newton, or Edison, or others, or Bell, or whoever, Einstein.
We rarely thank Allahسُبحانه وتعالى for these things.
Rarely do you find somebody saying; Alhamdulillah(اَلْحَمْدُ لله) for the car, or Alhamdulillah(اَلْحَمْدُ لله) who made communication easy,
or Alhamdulillah(اَلْحَمْدُ لله) who made transportation easier for us,
Alhamdulillah(اَلْحَمْدُ لله) who provided us with the telephone, or the car, or the airplane, or whatever.
Whenever we attribute the credit; we give the credit to the human being.
Now it's true, that this happened through the human being.
That is true!
But in the end, who is the one who made it possible for the human being to do it?
It's Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
When Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is talking about Dawoodعليه السلام particularly, making these shields.
What did  Allahسُبحانه وتعالى say?
وَعَلَّمْنَٰهُ صَنْعَةَ لَبُوسٍۢ لَّكُمْ لِتُحْصِنَكُم مِّنۢ بَأْسِكُمْ ۖ فَهَلْ أَنتُمْ شَٰكِرُونَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; We taught him how to make armoury for you, so are you going to be grateful?
Allah is telling the human beings; it is Dawood(داؤد) who made this for you.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى did not say; Be grateful to Dawood(داؤد).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; Be grateful to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Because, that is where the credit belongs.
So, whatever technological accessories we have; credit should go to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; The One, Who created everything.
It is from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, and it is a blessing from Allah.
And it is a test for the ones, who made these things.
And it's a test for the nations, who are producing these things for us; who are they giving credit to?
In France, there was a Muslim PhD student, who did an excellent research.
And then he wrote on the cover page of that PhD dissertation,
he said;
And all credit goes to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, and if there is any mistake in this research; it is because of me.
His professor who happens to be an atheist, he said;
You worked for years on this research, and then you give credit to someone who didn't do anything for you.
And you; the one who worked for four years; you say that, all mistakes belong to you.
What's wrong with you; Can't you think straight?
Now you're going to be a PhD student; I'm going to give you a PhD.
And you're still thinking in this backward mentality, the credit doesn't go to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
We should say, Alhamdulillah(اَلْحَمْدُ لله) for everything.
Alhamdulillah(اَلْحَمْدُ لله) for everything;
every tool; or every instrument; or every machine; or anything that we have around us, it came to us from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى through mankind.
You find that, many of these inventions were invented in what seems to be a random way.
I mean; the scientist was sitting down a tree, and then the apple fall down.
This might be a story, but with penicillin; we know for a fact that it came from a random observation.
They were studying something else and somehow, they discovered penicillin.
And with many other things, the scientists would be studying something, and then this thing comes along on the side,
and they found out about it and it turns out to be a greater invention, or a greater study; than the what they were studying before?
Who is turning their attention to these directions?
It's Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; they say; It happened randomly!
It's not random, everything is with the Qadar(قَدَر) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
It is Qadar(قَدَر) from Allah; Taqdeer(تقدير) from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
There is nothing that is haphazard and random in the universe.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَشَدَدْنَا مُلْكَهُۥ وَءَاتَيْنَٰهُ ٱلْحِكْمَةَ وَفَصْلَ ٱلْخِطَابِ۝
We made his kingdom strong, and gave him wisdom and sound judgment in speech and decision.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given him a strong kingdom, and we said that; this was the golden age of the children of Israel(اسرائيل).
The time of Dawood(داؤد) and Sulaimanعليه السلام.
That is, when their kingdom reached to its peak.
And that is when it was the kingdom of Tawheed(تؤحيد); the unity of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, and the Kingdom of Islam.
After that, the religion was changing and children of Israel(اسرائيل) were going down.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given him strength in his Kingdom; his kingdom was strong.
وَءَاتَيْنَٰهُ ٱلْحِكْمَةَ وَفَصْلَ ٱلْخِطَابِ۝
And Allah has given him wisdom, and the good judgment.
وَفَصْلَ ٱلْخِطَابِ۝
Allah has given him decisiveness.
Being decisive is important for somebody; who is in the position of Dawoodعليه السلام.
Dawood(داؤد) was a king.
And he had to deal with enemies, he had to deal with internal problems, he had to deal with many difficult conflicting situations.
Therefore, decisiveness is important in such a situation.
It is a quality that is needed for somebody in such a position.
When you're dealing with militaries, and you're dealing with enemies, and you're dealing with huge nations around you, and strong enemies; the issue of decisiveness is important.
And decisiveness also is needed in court.
See, there are some places where you need decisiveness, some places where it's not needed that much.
In court; it's also needed, you have to have the decisive judgment.
You can't go back and forth.
You can't have one foot to the left one foot to the right.
You have to have a clear understanding of the situation and then a clear judgment.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given Sayidina Dawood(سيدناداؤد); the decisiveness.
وَفَصْلَ ٱلْخِطَابِ۝
He had the ability to study the situation, and take a final judgment, and go ahead with it.
And then he would not retreat and not hesitate.
Dawoodعليه السلام reached to this stage, after he went through training.
See, people don't suddenly come out of nowhere with all of these qualities.
We learn things through our knowledge and life experiences.
Two sources; knowledge in one side and life experiences from the other side.
That is how we learn.
And that is why, we need to understand the importance of the concept of Tarbiyyah(تربيه).
Tarbiyyah(تربيه) is important in Islam.
Tarbiyyah(تربيه); training and raising up a person from one stage to another.
You cannot have a revolutionary sudden change.
Things have to go step by step.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى put the Sahabah(صحابه) in the furnace.
He put them through the tests, for years and years.
So, in the end, when they graduated; they graduated with the highest certificates.
Put the Sahabi(صحابي) in any situation; he will never fail.
Because, they went through trial after trial; test after test; in the School of Muhammadﷺ.
When they graduated in the end; Rasool Allah ﷺ knew that, he has left behind men, who can carry the message.
But they went through experiences, and they learned from their mistakes.
We're not born with all of the qualities.
The same with the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء), and with Rasool Allah ﷺ; Allah put him through 40 years of preparation.
He didn't become a prophet when he was born.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى planned the life of Muhammadﷺ day by day.
Everything in the life of Muhammadﷺ for the 40 years before Prophet-hood was, for a purpose.
And the same thing with Musaعليه السلام, we already talked about this; when he was raised in the palace of Firaun(فرعون).
That was an experience for him; and Yusufعليه السلام.
With Dawoodعليه السلام; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى also prepared him through some tests.
We're going to talk about one of these tests; a sample.
Dawood(داؤد) used to have a Mihrab(محراب); a place of worship,
where he would stay in seclusion; in solitude, and worship Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; away from everything; away from all distractions.
And he will not allow anyone to come in.
Suddenly, out of nowhere, two men appeared in front of Dawood(داؤد).
تصورٌمحراب
They jumped over; they climbed over, and suddenly, Sayidina Dawood(سيدناداؤد) saw two men in front of him.
So you can see that, there was an element of shock and surprise in this, right?
Suddenly, out of nowhere, you're in the depths of your Tasbeeh(تسبيح) and Dhikr(ذكر), and now you find two men standing in front of you; inside your house.
Sayidina Dawood(سيدناداؤد) was in a state of shock and surprise.
And they saw that he was worried, they said;
لا تخف
Don't worry!
They said;
وَهَلْ أَتَاكَ نَبَأُ الْخَصْمِ إِذْ تَسَوَّرُوا الْمِحْرَابَ۝
إِذْ دَخَلُواْ عَلَىٰ دَاوُۥدَ فَفَزِعَ مِنْهُمْ ۖ قَالُواْ لَا  تَخَفْ ۖ
خَصْمَانِ بَغَىٰ بَعْضُنَا عَلَىٰ بَعْضٍۢ فَٱحْكُم بَيْنَنَا بِٱلْحَقِّ وَلَا تُشْطِطْ
فَٱحْكُم بَيْنَنَا بِٱلْحَقِّ وَلَا تُشْطِطْ وَٱهْدِنَآ إِلَىٰ سَوَآءِ ٱلصِّرَٰطِ۝
We are too litigants; one of whom has wronged the other,
therefore a judge between us with truth, and treat us; not with unjustice, and guide us to the right way.
So, Davidعليه السلام was presented with the case.
These two men said, that we have a dispute, and we want you to judge upon us with justice and truth.
The case is as follows;
إِنَّ هَٰذَا أَخِي لَهُ تِسْعٌ وَتِسْعُونَ نَعْجَةً وَلِيَ نَعْجَةٌ وَاحِدَةٌ فَقَالَ
فَقَالَ أَكْفِلْنِيهَا وَعَزَّنِي فِي الْخِطَابِ۝
Verily this; my brother has 99 ewes; sheep, while I have only one sheep,
and he says, hand it over to me, and he overpowered me in speech.
One man is saying that, this; other person standing in front of you; has 99 ewes; sheep; female sheep.
And I have only one.
And he took away from me that one single sheep that I have, and he didn't give it back to me.
There are many stories about this Ayah(آية), but all of them are Israiliyat(اسرائيليات).
We're going to stay away from them, and we're going to stick with the Qur'an; with the Authentic.
So this man said; He has 99 sheep.
So he has much more than I do.
He's wealthier than me.
And I only have one and he overpowered me, he fooled me, he took me over with his beautiful words.
And I handed over to him my single sheep.
And now he doesn't want to give it back to me.
Dawoodعليه السلام give his judgment.
He said;
قَالَ لَقَدْ ظَلَمَكَ بِسُؤَالِ نَعْجَتِكَ إِلَىٰ نِعَاجِهِۦ ۖ
وَإِنَّ كَثِيرًا مِّنَ ٱلْخُلَطَآءِ لَيَبْغِى بَعْضُهُمْ عَلَىٰ بَعْضٍ إِلَّا ٱلَّذِينَ ءَامَنُواْ وَعَمِلُواْ ٱلصَّٰلِحَٰتِ
إِلَّا ٱلَّذِينَ ءَامَنُواْ وَعَمِلُواْ ٱلصَّٰلِحَٰتِ وَقَلِيلٌ مَّا هُمْ ۗ
David said; He has wronged you in demanding your ewe, in addition to his ewes.
And verily, many partners oppress one another except those who believe and do righteous good deeds; and they are few.
Dawoodعليه السلام said; that he has wronged you.
He shouldn't have taken away from you, your sheep.
And then, Dawood(داؤد) said; And partners; they always wrong each other, except the few believers.
Dawoodعليه السلام is telling us; this is thousands of years ago, that most of the time partners, they wrong each other.
Partnership usually find that, every partner is trying to take over the other.
And every partner is trying to outwit, or try to outsmart the other one.
And everyone is trying to work out the best deal for himself.
And that always happens between partners, and there is an exception to that, and these are the ones who believe.
And this is a warning to us, that whenever you have a partnership, have it very clear.
Have the terms clear written down.
That is very important in partnerships to have clear agreements.
When Dawood(داؤد) said that, the two men standing in front of him disappeared and vanished.
Without saying anything, they suddenly disappeared.
Dawood(داؤد) immediately knew that, this was a test from Allah, and that, he has committed a mistake.
He knew; he didn't need anybody to tell him.
What was the mistake of Sayidina Dawood(سيدناداؤد)?
He didn't listen to the other side.
He heard one side of the story, it sounded very appealing.
99 sheep, and you have only one, and he took it away from you?
Clear oppression.
He stole; I mean, this man has 99 sheep and you have only one, and he took it away from you.
And he gave his judgment.
He didn't hear from the other side.
And this was a test from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; Allah wants to test him.
Why?
Because Dawood(داؤد) is going to assume a very important responsibility and he needs to have patience and giving out his judgment.
And that's why they surprised him.
That element of surprise and shock was to knock Sayidina Dawood(سيدناداؤد) off his guard and suddenly present the case to him very fast.
So Sayidina Dawoodعليه السلام also gave his answer very fast.
So the whole setup was in a way, push Dawood(داؤد) to give fast or a hasty judgment.
And that is what happened.
It was a test from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى,
but Sayidina Dawood(سيدناداؤد) immediately realized that, it was a test from Allah and that, he has committed a mistake.
What was his reaction?
He made Sujood(سجود) to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
وَظَنَّ دَاوُودُ أَنَّمَا فَتَنَّاهُ فَاسْتَغْفَرَ رَبَّهُ وَخَرَّ رَاكِعًا وَأَنَابَ۝
And David guessed that, We have tried him, and sought forgiveness of his Lord, and he fell down prostrate, and turn to Allah in repentance.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَغَفَرْنَا لَهُۥ ذَٰلِكَ ۖ
We forgave him.
وَإِنَّ لَهُۥ عِندَنَا لَزُلْفَىٰ وَحُسْنَ مَـَٔابٍۢ۝
And for him is a near access to us, and a good place of final return.
After that, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
يَٰدَاوُۥدُ إِنَّا جَعَلْنَٰكَ خَلِيفَةً
Oh Dawood(داؤد)! We are appointing you as a Khalifah(خليفه); as a successor over mankind.
When did this happen?
After Dawood(داؤد) went through the test.
So the scholars say something interesting.
They say that, Dawood(داؤد) after the mistake, was better than Dawood(داؤد) before the mistake.
Even though, he committed a mistake; but Dawoodعليه السلام after the mistake was better than Dawoodعليه السلام before the mistake.
If we learn from our mistakes; we improve through our mistakes.
Because now, Dawood(داؤد) learn the right way to judge, and to be patient, and to listen from both sides, and not to be hasty in his judgment.
And that qualified him, to be king over mankind. Tawbah(توبة); repentance to Allah can make us better.
Why?
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
مَن تَابَ وَءَامَنَ وَعَمِلَ عَمَلًا صَٰلِحًا فَأُوْلَٰٓئِكَ يُبَدِّلُ ٱللَّهُ سَيِّـَٔاتِهِمْ حَسَنَٰتٍۢ ۗ
The ones who make repentance, and believe in Allah, and do good deeds;
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will change their bad deeds into good ones.
Not only, will Allah clear your account and you will start with a zero balance.
Not only that, but your previous sins will turn into good deeds.
So the evil, imagine it! This dirt; that you have in your past; will turn into pure gold.
Tawbah(توبة); that is Tawbah(توبة); learning from mistakes, but we need to repent.
Sayidina Dawood(سيدناداؤد); he asked Allah for forgiveness, Allah forgave him and he became better.
Same thing with Adamعليه السلام.
He became a prophet; when did he become a prophet?
Before the mistake or after?
He became a prophet after he committed his mistake; brought us down from Paradise.
He became a prophet after that.
So we learned from our mistakes.
But if we continue doing mistakes, and we don't get the lesson, and we don't get the point,
and we fail from test to test, we don't benefit anything and we become worse.
The point is to learn, and to benefit from the experiences that we have.
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said;
فَٱحْكُم بَيْنَ ٱلنَّاسِ بِٱلْحَقِّ وَلَا تَتَّبِعِ ٱلْهَوَىٰ
Rule among people with truth and; don't follow your desires.
Do not follow your desires;
why?
فَيُضِلَّكَ عَن سَبِيلِ ٱللَّهِ ۚ
For it will mislead you from the path of Allah.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
إِنَّ ٱلَّذِينَ يَضِلُّونَ عَن سَبِيلِ ٱللَّهِ لَهُمْ عَذَابٌ شَدِيدٌۢ بِمَا نَسُواْ يَوْمَ ٱلْحِسَابِ۝
Those who wander in stray from the path of Allah; will have a severe tournament.
Again, Allah is telling Dawood(داؤد); to judge among the people, and to rule among them, and to govern among them with?
Truth.
And do not follow your desire.
The most dangerous thing on the Islamic judicial system is following desires.
The most dangerous thing in our relations with one another; is when we base it on our own desires and not on the law of Allah.
And as we say, in Arabic, and I think this saying is also in English;
العدل في قلب القاضي
Justice is in the heart of the judge.
The law can be on paper.
But if the judge does not want to apply it, he can find ways around it.
You can.
Therefore justice is in the heart of the judge.
And that is why, we can only have justice through true Islamic system.
Why?
Because you either have good laws and a corrupt judge, or you have a good judge and corrupt laws.
In the Muslim world; now, in most of the places, we have a corrupt law with a corrupt judge.
We have them both.
Here in America; you have a corrupt law, but sometimes you have a good judge, sometimes you don't.
The combination that we want, is a good law and the good judge.
And that could only happen when the law is Islamic, and when the heart of the judge is Islamic.
But if the heart of the judge is not Islamic, no matter how good the law is.
If it is Quran sitting on his desk; it wouldn't do anything.
If the heart of the judge is not in line with the law; it won't do anything.
Because we have in some Muslim countries; Islamic law on paper, we do!
In many Muslim countries, for example; the laws relating to the family are Islamic.
Divorce and marriage, and their children rights, and all that and women, the divorced and the widow, most of that is Islamic.
But the problem is with the heart of the judge.
Bribery and all those other problems.
When we talk about Shariah(شريعة); unfortunately, this is another problem that we have.
Now, we all say we want Shariah(شريعة)! We want Shariah(شريعة)!
But then, when we look at it; we find that what the people are looking for; isn't really Shariah(شريعة).
I mean; you find many people say, ask them; What is your definition of Shariah(شريعة)?
Why are you asking for Shariah(شريعة)?
He says; We want them to cut the hand of the one who steals, and to kill the killer, and to stone the adulterer.
Is that Shariah(شريعة)?
Is that all, what Shariah(شريعة) is about?
And then they would say; This certain country or that place is applying Shariah(شريعة),
why?
Because they would cut the hand of the one who steals, and they would kill the killer.
This is only part of a section of the Islamic law; which is the criminal code, the criminal law; that's it.
I mean; do you think that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has sent all of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء), and all of the religions;
just to cut the hand of the one who steals, and to stone the adulterer, and to kill the killer?
And then also what segment of the society do these people make; the thieves, and the killers, and the rapists, and the adulterers?
What proportion do they make?
It's a minority of the society.
So all what Islam does is; deal with these people, and the rest of us; we don't have any law to apply to us?
Is that the Islamic law?
Is that Shariah(شريعة)?
That's not Shariah(شريعة); that is only part of the Islamic law which is relating to the criminal code, or the criminal section of law.
The Islamic Shariah(شريعة); that we are searching for is; based on one important pillar and that is; justice!
Justice for everyone!
If you're going to court; you will get a fair trial; the judge will treat you justly; preserving the rights of others.
Justice is an important pillar.
And then the Shariah(شريعة)!
The Shariah(شريعة); is to apply the religion of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى completely.
Now let's look at the four Khulafa(خُلَفَاء); which are our standard that we look at.
Take Abu Bakr(ابوبكر); the first Khalifah(خليفه).
During all the time of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر); we don't know in history, that he has stoned any adulterer.
Does it mean that, Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was not applying Shariah(شريعة)?
This case never showed up in his time.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was busy with applying Shariah(شريعة) day and night.
What was he doing?
The establishment of Islam, by fighting the Murtaddeen(مرتدين), and establishing a strong Islamic government.
That was applying the Shariah(شريعة).
So he was dealing with this project, and that is Shariah(شريعة).
And then, in the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب); he came and found stability, that was left behind from Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق).
The Islamic Khilafah(خِلَافَه) was already stable; Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not have to do anything.
It was stabilized by Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق).
Now, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) has to establish the institutions.
Because you already have stability; now you are establishing institutions.
So he made Ad-Deewan(الديوان), which is the Treasury; to take care of the salaries of the government employees and the army.
And then he establish new ways and laws to divide the land among Muslims.
And then he started; paving the roads and making these infrastructure services for the Muslim ummah(امة).
And then, he worked on a some other projects which were dealing with the very, very important rule of the Khalifah(خليفه), and that is the issue of Jihad(جهاد).
And he is the one, who took care of the Jihad(جهاد) with the Persian Empire.
By the time, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) died; Persian Empire was dead; It was over with.
Because the Persian Empire was the stumbling block; between Islam and the east.
The Persian Empire was that wall, that was preventing Islam from getting into the east.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) eliminated that wall.
So by the time of Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان); Islam was spreading all over Central Asia.
And then, Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان); what was his Shariah(شريعة)?
What was the establishing of Shariah(شريعة) in the time of Uthman(عثمان)?
He worked on a very important project, and that is; the preservation of Qur'an.
That is Shariah(شريعة).
And also spreading towards the east and continuing with the Futuhat(فتوحات) towards the north.
And then, the time of Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب); he had to deal with internal conflicts; which were in the Muslim Ummah(امۃ).
So, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) devoted his time of Khalifah(خليفه), which was four years; to solve this internal conflict,
that was caused by the death of Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) by the assassination of Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان).
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) had to deal with that problem for four years.
And then, in the time of Muawiya Ibn Abu-Sufyan(معاويه ابن ابو سفيان); he came to deal with other problems.
So, he is the first one to establish the Islamic Navy.
Because, now the Muslims need to go in the sea, and they need to spread towards the north and the Roman Empire.
So he is the first one to establish the Islamic Navy; that is Shariah(شريعة);
that is the establishment of Shariah(شريعة); to work on these projects which would serve the Muslim Ummah(امة).
So, the Muslims in the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) or in the times of these Khulafa(خُلَفَاء); they would live with peace and security.
They would travel from the east to the west, and the Muslim ummah(امة) fearing no one, but Allah; safety and security.
They would do their business and they would not worry.
They would leave their stores open, and go to Salah(صلوة); this is the establishment of Shariah(شريعة).
And this is what, we are looking for.
It's not an issue of just establishing this issue of Shariah(شريعة), which is important obviously the criminal law.
Because you cannot have security; unless the criminals are put on check.
But Shariah(شريعة) is larger than that.
Shariah(شريعة) encompasses everything that is Islamic.
اقامت الدين
Establishment of the religion of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And the very, very, very important thing for the leader.
وَلَا تَتَّبِعِ ٱلْهَوَىٰ
Don't follow your desires.
Our problem; our problem now, with Islamic work; is that we always deal with others based on our desires.
I have a certain problem with you.
I continue with that problem, to justify it from an Islamic point of view.
So it's not Islam that is instigating my dealing with you.
It is my hatred towards you and then I'm using Islam to fulfill it.
No, we should instigate our actions based on Islam.
And then we push our desires to follow the direction of the Shariah(شريعة).
Wherever Islam goes; that is where, we push our desire.
And this is the Jihad(جهاد) of the Nafs(نفس).
You don't do things according to what you want.
You do things according to what Allah wants.
You do it Allah's way, not your way.
And that is a very difficult discipline.
And that is a very difficult and important Jihad(جهاد);
the Jihad(جهاد) of your soul to fight these internal conflicts that are going in your heart;
to follow the law of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, and to follow what Allah wants from you, and that is the meaning of the word; Islam; to submit to Allah.
That is what it means; submission.
So you submit your will to Allah.
You follow what Allah wants from you.
سَمِعْنَا وَأَطَعْنَا
We listen and we obey.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تسلیما کثیرہ